Daf ע"ח *Ayin Chet* 78, we're actually a little bit ahead. So
we pick up in the middle of ע"ח *Ayin Chet* on the
two dots about, I don't know, 15 lines down, actually the beginning
of a line. ושאר כל המשקין ברביעית *Veshear kol hamashkin berivi'it*. So
we're finishing up looking at the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* that deals with
the different amounts for taking out different liquids, and some liquids was
a smaller amount, honey to put on a wound, water to use
for some type of an eye ointment or a pack, and so
on. It was very interesting, the last thing we saw yesterday was
a nice abstraction by אביי *Abaye*, like pointing out the principle. He
said, "Look, if you have a common use and an uncommon use,
we go by the common use, even if that means a קולא
*Kula*, more lenient amount, but that's the most common of the object.
If there are multiple common uses, then we'll go by the strictest
one because then that's a legitimate, that even with that small amount,
that is of a, that's a reason, that's a, that gives it
value, that's a reason why people would see it as significant." And
that was important, that's just helpful in terms of understanding why they're
picking different types of things. Of course, the question still is, like
the water issue which אביי *Abaye* raised, is that water is much
more used for drinking than it is for other things, but somehow
if that's a very common, if it's commonly needed when you're making
an eye pack, then that makes water,
that's considered like a common use
of water. So it's interesting even how you define common use, it's
interesting what population you look at, like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort
of spoke about, maybe in the Galilee it's different than in other
places, would the שיעור *Shiur* actually change based on different locations? That's
also a question we've been asking, how much are these שיעורים *Shiurim*
malleable based on changing circumstances, how much once they've been fixed they've
been fixed.
So a lot of interesting issues we've been looking at. Now we
wrap up this discussion by the last line, or second to last
line: ושאר כל המשקין ברביעית *Veshear kol hamashkin berivi'it*. And all other
liquids go by רביעית revi'it. *Revi'it* other than
the specific exceptions we mentioned before. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan. *Tanu rabanan*,
so our Rabbis taught: דם וכל מיני משקין ברביעית *Dam vechol minei
mashkin berivi'it*. Blood and all liquids. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* takes out the
word וכל *Vechol*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says דם ושאר מיני משקה *Dam
veshear minei mashke* because it means all other liquids that we have
not yet mentioned. You know, we mentioned some that were not a
רביעית revi'it. *Revi'it*, but other ones, including even blood, are a רביעית
revi'it *Revi'it*. Okay. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar אומר
דם כדי לכחול עין אחת kedei lichol ayin achat, *Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar omer dam kedei lichol ayin achat*. No, blood is not a
רביעית revi'it, *Revi'it*. Blood, I mean you start wondering what do you
need blood for and so on, is it just a catchall category,
רביעית revi'it *Revi'it*? Is there really, even if it's not like a
drink, it's a רביעית revi'it, *Revi'it*? So does it really make sense
that all other liquids are רביעית revi'it, *Revi'it*? Anyway, so at least
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* argues by
the blood. And he says, enough blood in order to basically like
paint one eye. כחול Kachol, *Kachol* is, can sometimes mean like a
type of a blue powder paint, sometimes it refers to a paint
they put on the eye, sometimes it refers to some type of
application they put in the eye for a type of a medicinal
purpose. Anyway, apparently they would sometimes use blood as a type of,
I don't know, rouge or something. So for עין אחת *Ayin achat*,
one eye. Why? שכן כוחלין לברקית *Sheken kochlin levarakit*, because you actually
put this on for ברקית *Barakit*, which רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says is
some type of a like of a mote, is that what it's
called? A mote. Some type of a bump in the eye. So
therefore, and they would apply this a little blood into the eye
for that purpose. So because it was for, if it was for
cosmetics, presumably it would be both eyes, it would be on the
outside.
But it doesn't matter if you can do it on שבת Shabbat,
*Shabbat*.
But it doesn't matter if you can do it on שבת Shabbat
*Shabbat*. It matters if you're carrying on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*, it matters
if this is an amount of significance in general, even if it's
not of significance today on שבת *Shabbat*, right? You don't change it
day by day. Since the rest of the week you would use
that amount, so it doesn't have to be a use you could
use it for on שבת *Shabbat*. Let's say for example, like take
out a match, okay? I'm חייב chayav *Chayav* because, but I can't
strike the match on שבת *Shabbat*. Yeah, but a match is an
object of significance. So it doesn't have to be that you can
use it on שבת *Shabbat*. Okay, so that's what he says, that
you could use it for a medicinal purpose. ומאי ניהו *Umai nihu*?
And what, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, what type of blood
is it that you would apply to the eye if it had
this like bump? דמא דתרנגולא ברא bara, *Dama detarnagola bara*. It's the,
it's the blood of a wild rooster. So now that's interesting. So
you would apply the blood of a wild rooster to this bump.
Does that mean that he says all blood therefore goes by that
amount, or just the blood of a wild rooster? Very unclear exactly
how this translates. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. רבן גמליאל
אומר דם כדי לכחול בו עין אחת שכן כוחלין לאירד *Rabban Gamliel
omer dam kedei lichol bo ayin achat sheken kochlin la'erod*. He says,
I agree that it's one eye, but for a different reason. What's
the different reason? That they use it for, to put on for
medicinal purposes for אירד *Erod*, which just reminding myself what רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says that it is,
right, white spot, right, white spots, which is for some type of
a white spots. ומאי ניהו *Umai nihu*? What type of blood would
they use for that? דמא ד *Dama de*... דמא דכרשוטינא,
the blood of a bat, רש״י Rashi says is what it means.
וסימנך, ve-simancha, how do you remember which blood you use for what
problem? So גווא לגווא, gavva le-gavva, out for the out, meaning wild
rooster which is the word ברא, which means outside. Thank you. So
therefore things that are in the wild on the outside for something
that protrudes out for a bump. Okay, גווא לגווא, gavva le-gavva, something
on the inside, a bat, you could have said maybe it's inside
of caves, רש״י Rashi says it also means it's in the city,
there would be bats in the city and therefore that's for something
that's inner, the bump, the dots that are inside the pupil of
the eye. All right, very nice, but again the question is, are
they saying all bloods are this, are חייב chayav for this small
amount or only this particular blood is חייב chayav, for this small
amount? Not clear.
Now the גמרא Gemara continues, במה דברים אמורים במוציא. bameh devarim amurim
bemotzi. When is this true that you're חייב, chayav, you go by
this amount when you are when you just when you take it
out. אבל במצניע, aval be-matznia, if it's not talking about the person
who took it out, it's talking about the מצניע, matznia, now again
because of the way the grammar works in Hebrew, you know, מצניע
matznia could mean two things, you know, you could be the you
could be the in a case where
in circumstances where במצניע, be-matznia, you know, that you are that that's
being put aside, or במצניע, be-matznia, the one who is מצניע matznia
it, and we'll see how גמרא Gemara reads it that way. אבל
במצניע כל שהוא aval be-matznia kol shehu חייב, chayav. even the smallest
amount you're חייב. chayav. So if you basically for the case where
it was seek, you know, put aside as we learned in the
משנה, Mishnah, if you you know if these are standard sizes, but
if you actually took this small a small amount and put it
aside because you valued it and you were setting it aside, therefore
even if you take out that small amount you're חייב. chayav, So
the גמרא Gemara says,
okay where is it, כל שהוא. kol shehu. רבי שמעון אומר במה
דברים אמורים במצניע, Rabbi Shimon omer bameh devarim amurim be-matznia, did I
just read that? Yeah. במה דברים אמורים במצניע אבל במוציא אינו חייב
אלא ברביעית. bameh devarim amurim be-matznia aval bemotzi eino chayav ela bi-revi'it.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says if you remember this is really playing
out the debate in the משנה, Mishnah, that the first approach said
these are the standard amounts but if you set it aside it's
even less, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon went in the opposite direction.
He said no, these are the amounts that are if you set
it aside because then you could be under a רביעית. revi'it. But
if you haven't set it aside, then all of these things, even
the blood and the honey and the milk and all those things
we talked about yesterday that were smaller sizes, if you haven't specifically
set them aside and shown their importance, it would go up to
a רביעית. revi'it. So this is the debate, right? You have רביעית
revi'it as like a type of one possibility, you have the smaller
sizes we discussed for certain liquids, and you have the possibility of
כל שהוא. kol shehu. So the first opinion of the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, which it sounded like sounds like our משנה, Mishnah is
these smaller sizes are for these various liquids that are significant even
smaller sizes, that's the standard. If you actually set set it aside,
then it's even כל שהוא, kol shehu, then it's even more strict.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon... בן אלעזר goes in the opposite direction. No,
these smaller sizes than a רביעית, Revi'it? that's because you set them
aside and because you gave them significance. If you didn't set them
aside, then it goes up to the רביעית revi'it and that's the
standard for the default for all liquids even for these things like
the honey and the milk and so on. Okay so that's basically
if you remember the debate in the משנה Mishnah. being restated here
in the ברייתא. Beraita. But the גמרא Gemara, is going to have
a concern with it and we'll see in a minute. ומודים חכמים
לרבי שמעון במוציא שופכין ששיעורן
ברביעית. u-modim chachamim le-Rabbi Shimon bemotzi shofchin she-shi'uran bi-revi'it. Rabbis agree to
רבי Rebbi שמעון Shimon that he says look, we're saying that there's
a standard even in non-special cases of smaller sizes by you know
various things, honey, milk, etc. But stuff like dirty
water there, you know, that's going that where we agree that's going
to be a רביעית, revi'it that is not going to be this
lesser size. Okay, so that is that is the debate and now
we take a look at how what what the ברייתא Beraita says
on it. One minute,
right.
Did I skip a line? I'm just רבי שמעון... No,
I find. Okay. אמר מר, Amar mar,
thank you. אמר מר. Amar mar. במה דברים אמורים במוציא אבל במצניע
כל שהוא. bameh devarim amurim bemotzi aval be-matznia kol shehu. So this
is the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma opinion that all these small sizes
are in a normal case of carrying. But if you actually set
them aside, then it actually becomes even a כל שהוא. kol shehu.
So גמרא Gemara says, אטו מצניע לאו מוציא הוא? atu matznia lav
motzi hu? Is the setting aside aren't you also the מוציא? motzi?
So meaning the what's exactly is the question? I'll tell you תוספות's
Tosafot version which is a little smoother than רש״י. Rashi. תוספות's Tosafot
version is like this, it says במצניע be-matznia it reads it as
not just in a case where it was set aside, but for
the one who set it aside, המצניע. ha-matznia. So the גמרא Gemara
so if you read it that way it says for המצניע ha-matznia
is a
I'm sorry wait a minute let me double check תוספות Tosafot because
this is actually between רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot's hold on.
No, okay, yeah, רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot read it in exact
opposite ways, but I'll read תוספות's Tosafot way. Okay, but
תוספות Tosafot says the opposite. If it said המצניע בכל שהוא, hamatznia
bechol shehu, then it would mean the person who set it aside,
for him it's only for only for him it's a בכל שהוא.
bechol shehu. But for other people, hold on, I'm just getting confused
again one second.
Right, right. Okay, so had it said המצניע בכל שהוא, hamatznia bechol
shehu, then it would have meant for the person who set it
aside it's a בכל שהוא. bechol shehu. And that's what we expected
in our משנה. Mishnah The משנה Mishnah said that if you set
it aside, then for you it's important, for you it's a בכל
שהוא. bechol shehu. But it didn't. It said במצניע בכל שהוא, bimatznia
bechol shehu, which means in a case when it was put aside,
not necessarily you put it aside, in a case it was put
aside. So that could mean that, you know, that David here put
it aside and I took it out. Now you might remember that
was in the משנה Mishnah there was an opinion רב שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar said even if somebody else puts it
aside, the example I gave you, right, I took out my chewing
gum, I put it aside, so the first opinion of the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma is when I take out my chewing gum I'm
חייב, chayav. but for you it's not, that's like not value. Okay,
that's but because I gave it significance I put it aside to
chew later, for me I'm going to be חייב. chayav Then you
had the position of רב שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
that says if I put it aside even when you take it
out you're חייב chayav? because once I've given it significance it now
has significance for everybody. So when the משנה Mishnah. when the ברייתא
Braita here said במצניע בכל שהוא, bimatznia bechol shehu, the way תוספות
Tosafot understands the גמרא, Gemara if it said המצניע בכל שהוא hamatznia
bechol shehu it means me, the one who put it aside my
chewing gum, when I take it out I'm חייב בכל שהוא. chayav
bechol shehu. But when it says במצניע bimatznia it means in a
case when it was put aside it's בכל שהוא, bechol shehu, even
if David takes out my chewing gum it's בכל שהוא. bechol shehu.
And that's the גמרא Gemara says, really? That's רב שמעון בן אלעזר?
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar? That's a crazy opinion, we don't hold like
that. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara goes.
What is בכל שהוא?
bechol shehu?
The smallest amount. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says במה דברים אמורים, bameh
devarim amurim, let's read that again, במוציא, bemotzi, אבל במצניע, aval bimatznia,
in a case when it was put aside בכל שהוא, bechol shehu,
even a small amount. אטו מצניע
לאו מוציא הוא? atu matznia lav motzi hu? Which basically the way
תוספות Tosafot reads it is, you know, המצניע, hamatznia, I'm sorry, that
should be מצניע לאו מוציא הוא. matznia lav motzi hu. The one
who put it aside is not the one who took it out,
and you know that we shouldn't how how can it be that
somebody who didn't the person who didn't put it aside is going
to be חייב? chayav. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, הכא במאי עסקינן,
hacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about? בתלמיד שאמר לו רבו,
betalmid she'amar lo rabbo, לך ופנה לי המקום לסעודה. lech u'pne li
hamakom liseudah. A master said to a student, רש״י Rashi says it
doesn't mean like a רבי and a student, it means like, you
know, a it's talking about like an apprentice. So, you know, the
master says to the apprentice, anyway go and clear out from this
place we're having a meal. והלך ופנה לו דבר חשוב לכל חייב
עליה. vehalach u'pina lo davar chashuv lachol chayav alei. And the apprentice
has to do everything the master says.
והלך ופנה לו דבר חשוב. vehalach u'pina lo davar chashuv. And he
went out and he took all the stuff out, he cleared out
the room, but what he did is unfortunately he cleared out the
room by taking the stuff out into the street, which is carry.
So if he took out into the street something that everybody would
agree is significant,
חייב. chayav דבר שאינו חשוב לכל, davar she'eino chashuv lachol,
if most people would think that thing he took outside does not
have significance, it's less than the minimum size of significance, אי אצנייה
רבו, ei atniyeh rabbo, if his master had specifically given it significance,
set it aside, מחייב עליה, michayiv alei, he's חייב chayav for it.
ואי לא לא מחייב, ve'ee lo lo michayiv, and if not, not.
So what does all this mean? It means like this. Again, I
set aside my chewing gum. I'm חייב chayav. when I take it
out. That's what we saw since even though normally the sizes are
more, I put it aside for chewing later, I gave it significance,
I'm going to be חייב. chayav? How about David here? Is he
going to be חייב? chayav According to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
no. You have a position of רב שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar that says even David is going to be חייב chayav.
when I put aside my chewing gum, it's now significant for everybody
because I gave it significance. This ברייתא Braita said
sounded like it was saying that second opinion, in a case where
it was put aside anybody is חייב. chayav? Okay, and that's the
גמרא Gemara said that's a completely rejected opinion. How could we be
saying that? So the first how could you say המצניע hamatznia if
the person who put aside is not the person who took it
out, how could you be חייב? chayav So it says there's one
special case where somebody else could be חייב chayav even according to
the way we פוסקין, poskin, which is that David here is my
apprentice and my שמש. shamash. And since he has to do everything
I tell him, the things that I give significance wind up being
defined as being significant to him because his sort of position is
one in which he has to attend to all of my needs
and do everything that I say. So in that case when I
put aside my chewing gum and I tell David to take out
take out my chewing gum, because of his relationship to me that's
an object of significance for him as well. But in all other
cases, the only person who would be חייב chayav, would be the
person who had actual had set it aside. Okay, so the upshot
of all of this is is that by אוכלים, ochlin, by foods
we always go by כגרוגרת, kegrogeret, which is like a pressed fig.
By liquids, a standard is a רביעית, revi'it but there is a
whole range of exceptions of. milk and honey and blood maybe be
debated which are less than a רביעית. revi'it Not clear if everything
that's not in that list always has a use by a רביעית.
revi'it, There's some liquids that in the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask that in a minute about dirty water. But anyway that's the
standard except with a few exceptions. And if I actually got my
way and put something aside, then it goes down to a כלשהו
kol shehu at least for me. You got a question Ari? Okay.
So let's see now as the גמרא Gemara wraps this up. אמר
מר, Amar Mar, מודים חכמים לרבי שמעון במוציא שפכין לרשות הרבים, modim
chachamim l'rabbi Shimon b'motzi shpochin l'reshut harabim, ששיעורן ברביעית. sheshiuran b'revi'it.
But everybody agrees that something like dirty water is a רביעית revi'it
even if
it has no smaller size.
I don't know if I set it aside maybe, but anyway under
normal circumstances doesn't have a smaller size.
That's a very small amount, like why would you bother? רביעית?
Like yeah. So that's the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. Anyway,
something you can drink you understand, it's like a small little cup,
it's three and a half ounces. But the גמרא Gemara is going
to say שפכין למאי חזו? shpochin l'mai chazu? What do you use
dirty water for? So אמר רבי ירמיה, Amar rabbi Yirmiyah, לגבל בהן
את הטיט. l'gabel bahen et hatit. You use it because you can
use it to make plaster out of. So you might not use
it for drinking, but making plaster. Now since when is a רביעית
significant? It does seem like רביעית becomes a default if we don't
have a good way of determining another measure. Anyway so let's take
a look. ותניא בטיט V'tanya b'tit and in a ברייתא, braita, טיט
כדי לעשות פי כור, tit k'dei la'asot pi kur, that if you
are actually taking out
plaster on שבת, then it's the amount of plaster which you would
use to make like an opening for a bellows. A bellows is
this thing you blow air into when you're sort of doing smelting.
And apparently they would make some type of a plaster maybe to
like a wind tunnel or something to push the air. So anyway
you'd make that out of plaster. So the amount of plaster required
to make that. Now that is
a smaller amount, hold on a minute.
Right. So
that is much smaller than the amount of plaster you can make
with a רביעית of water. You take a רביעית of water, you
got a lot of sand, you can make a significant amount of
plaster, much more than the small amount you need to make this
like little opening for the bellows. So the גמרא Gemara says look,
if a plaster to make an opening for a bellows is enough
of significance, then the water to make that amount of plaster should
be enough of significance and it should be much less than a
רביעית, right? Do you sort of get the logic? So let's take
a look what the גמרא Gemara. says.
לא קשיא, Lo kashya, that's not difficult.
הא דמיגבל הא דלא מיגבל. Ha d'migbal ha d'lo migbal. It's a
difference whether it's already made into plaster or not yet made into
plaster. לפי שאין אדם טורח לגבל טיט לעשות פי כור. Lefichei she'ein
adam tore'ach l'gabel tit la'asot pi kur. I'm not going to go
ahead and start mixing my plaster mix just to make a little
this little type of a thing. I don't go to the effort
of making it until I've got a larger amount that I'm going
to use and that I have a purpose for. If I already
have made plaster, then even a small amount will be significant because
I can use it for a small amount, but unmade plaster I'm
not going to make it into plaster unless I have a more
significant amount. And therefore I would need a רביעית of water even
though it would create a lot more plaster than the amount that's
needed for this function. Okay, so that is the various liquids. Let's
continue now in the next משנה. mishna המוציא חבל, Hamotzi chevel, now
we go out of foodstuffs and we go to various other random
items. So המוציא חבל, hamotzi chevel, if you take out a rope
כדי לעשות אוזן לקופה, k'dei la'asot ozen l'kupa, it's in order to
make a ear for a box, meaning a handle for a box.
Okay, so you want to attach a rope to the box to
make a handle for it, that's the smallest normal use somebody would
have for a rope.
גמי, Gami, if you have a type of a like
not a rope, I mean what's it called, like a rubber, something
rubber, something elastic,
so strap or something of that nature, כדי לעשות תלאי לנפה ולכברה,
k'dei la'asot tlai l'nafa u'lkvarah, to make as a hanging loop for
a sieve. You know, so you like hang them in the kitchen
or whatever, you have a loop. We have little handles on them,
but you would make a strap to hang it from. Okay, so
that's the smallest use. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, כדי ליטול
ממנו מידת מנעל לקטן. k'dei litol mimenu midat minal l'katan. No, even
a presumably even a smaller amount, amount to use as a measure
for a shoe
for a small child. So basically you want to go to the
shoemaker
and get a shoe for your kid, you don't want to שלעפ
schlep your kid to the shoemaker because that's always a little bit
of a scene.
So what you do is you measure the kid's foot size at
home and then you take the string to the shoemaker to show
here's his shoe size and then you get the shoe. Okay, so
it's the amount of this type of strap that you would need
to do that measurement for. נייר, Niyar, now let's say you have
paper which is not קלף, klaf, it's paper, כדי לכתוב עליו קשר
מוכסין. k'dei lichtov alav kesher mochin. In order to write on it,
it's called a knot of the tax collectors, but presumably it's some.
type of a sign and a symbol, we'll see later it seems
like it's some two letters of tax collectors to basically serve as
a receipt that you paid your taxes. והמוציא קשר מוכסין חייב, Vehamotzi
kesher mochsin chayav, and if it is a קשר מוכסין, kesher mochsin,
if it is a receipt, you're also חייב, chayav which fits in
relatively obvious, but okay. נייר, Niyar, now on עין חית עמוד ב,
Ayin Chet amud bet, if it's נייר מחוק, niyar machuk, if it's
erased paper, and you can't write on erased paper because of what
they had for ways of writing and ways of erasing and types
of paper, so what good is erased paper? כדי לכרוך על צלוחית
קטנה Kedei lichroch al tzlochit ktana in order to wrap around a
little
flask, a little bottle של פלייטון shel playton of, remember that bottle
of פלייטון playton which women would wear around their neck and it
would carry out and would it be carrying on שבת or not
was discussed. Anyway so you have that little bottle of perfume and
you take a little piece of paper and wrap it around, wrap
it around to seal it like we would say like a little
piece of cloth.
Okay, or a leather כדי לעשות קמיע kedei la'asot kame'a enough to
make a קמיע, kame'a, an amulet. So there's an obvious conversation between
this משנה Mishna and the other משניות mishnayot about what people were
wearing, right? So they were wearing these things and then that amount
of that material therefore has significance. קלף, Claf, so we'll take out
the דוכסוסטוס, duchsustos, so we'll go to the next one. קלף, Claf,
if it's parchment כדי לכתוב עליו פרשה קטנה שבבתפילין, kedei lichtov alav
parsha ktana shebitfillin, the amount to write a small פרשה parsha of
the smallest פרשה parsha of תפילין tfillin שהיא שמע ישראל, she'hi Shema
Yisrael, which is שמע ישראל Shema Yisrael and that would go in
a separate compartment, the different פרשיות parshiyot each one so that's the
paragraph, not the words, those two words, the whole paragraph of שמע
ישראל. Shema Yisrael. Now parchment is much more expensive than paper. So
you would have intuitively assumed that less parchment that you'd be חייב
chayav for a smaller amount of parchment. But רש״י Rashi makes the
point that no, that because parchment is more expensive, you don't use
it for trivial uses. You don't use it for writing tax collector
receipts. You're only going to use your parchment for like something like
תפילין tfillin for writing the שמע Shema on. So that's a larger
size than the paper. The little tax collector's receipt is a smaller
size. So although this is more valuable, because it's not used except
in a larger size, you're not חייב chayav. unless it's the larger
size. So it's a little counterintuitive, but it makes sense. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, משנה mishna says, דיו, Dyo, ink, כדי לכתוב
בשתי אותיות, kedei lichtov beshtei otiyot, enough to write two letters. Two
letters can already have significance. רש״י Rashi says you can put
insert פ pe into
flask א. alef. So you write a letter on each thing and
you combine them. Two letters in general is considered writing on שבת.
So therefore enough ink for it is חייב. chayav,
כחול, kachol this is that eye shadow again or something applied on
the eye or in the eye, כדי לכחול עין אחת, one eye.
Again like before we talked about the blood, here we're talking about
the standard כחול which is like this blue type of a powder
or some type of a thing that was put on the eye
or in the eye, and even for one eye suffices, and we'll
see in the גמרא Gemara why one and not two eyes. What
use you would have for one eye. דבק, Devek, glue, כדי ליתן
בראש השפשף, kedei liten berosh hashafshaf, to put on the top of
a board that you hope pigeons will fly on and get trapped
on. It would be a glue trap. So the amount of glue
you would use for that. זפת וגופרית, Zefet vegofrit,
tar and pitch, כדי לעשות נקב, kedei la'asot nekev,
in order to make a hole. It doesn't really mean a hole,
you don't make a hole with pitch, but what it means is
that you make a,
רש״י Rashi says
that you would use this for if you had some type of
a thing that contained silver, like quicksilver, like mercury, then you would
seal it with this tar and pitch and you would make a
little
hole in it as a way of dripping it out. So basically
it would be the amount of tar and pitch you need to
seal, to cover an opening of a certain type of a
vessel, and the whole point is really just that you would be
making a hole in the pitch. But anyway, just to say, you're
not making a hole with the tar and the pitch, you're making
the seal with the tar and the pitch, but it just has
the hole in it. So that's basically the point. Okay, so the
amount of tar and pitch you would use to cover a vessel
which you would then sort of adjust. What?
Here it says the amount that you would use to seal that
small hole.
To seal the hole that it's in.
Sounds really
small.
Yeah, not the way רש״י Rashi sounds.
רש״י Rashi sounds you cover the vessel with the pitch and you
happen to make a hole in that pitch, but he doesn't say...
Yeah, I mean the language sounds like that. The language sounds
like כדי לעשות נקב. kedei la'asot nekev. And that's why so... anyway
I'll look into it more but I think the language of the
משנה Mishnah. and the language and what רש״י Rashi says. seems to
reflect is not that. It's the amount in which you would make
a hole, not to fill the hole, but the amount of thing
in which you would make the hole, you know, when it's covering
the vessel. Anyway, that's the tar and the pitch. שעוה shaavah wax,
כדי ליתן על פי נקב קטן. k'dei litein al pi nekev katan.
You see there, it's to stop a hole. The amount of wax
is to put over the opening of a small hole. That's different
from to make in it a hole. Okay, so that's the flax,
that's the wax. חרסית charasit which is like ground up pottery, כדי
לעשות פי כור של צורפי זהב. k'dei laasot pi kur shel tzorfei
zahav. That's what I mentioned before, that they would make a type
of of an opening for the bellows, for the, you know, for
the air to be pushed in when they were smelting. So the
type of you would use, obviously you'd have some crushed pottery with
water, you'd make it into some type of a plaster, and you
would make this type of a small of a small tube or
small opening and that would be the minimum amount. רבי יהודה אומר
Rabbi Yehuda omer כדי לעשות פיטפוט k'dei laasot pitput
in order to make a type of a tripod, a leg of
a tripod. סובין subin how about
bran, כדי ליתן על פי כור של צורפי זהב k'dei litein al
pi kur shel tzorfei zahav to put by by the mouth of
this bellows thing that you make for gold smelting? I really don't
exactly understand how they would use the bran, but somehow it serves
some purpose.
סיד sid plaster, כדי לסוד קטנה שבבנות k'dei lasud ktana shebabanot in
order to plaster a very small girl. What did it mean plaster?
They would use this as a way of removing hair. They would
put plaster on the skin and then pull off the plaster. I
mean they even do that nowadays to some degree, right? Right, don't
they have some things you you put on the—yeah, but like also
put what is it a wax treatment, right? And then right like
women who wax their legs, right? So that's what they would do,
but it's interesting it sounds like they would do it even for
very small girls. You know, how small girls, when do girls start
getting anyway hair on their skin? I mean presumably once they're the
age that they would actually use it. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda
omer כדי לעשות קילקל. k'dei laasot kilkel. He says no, in order
to make it as some type of a thing which was basically
to remove hair by the temple. ורבי נחמיה אומר ve-Rabbi Nechemya omer
כדי לסוד אונדפי k'dei lasud undefi which is also some type of
a removing hair near the temple. We'll see about that in the
גמרא. Gemara Okay, so now let's take a look at what the
גמרא Gemara has to say about all this. So the גמרא Gemara
says: חבל נמי ליחייב כדי
לעשות תלוי לנפה ולכברה. chevel nami lechayeiv k'dei laasot talui l'nafa u-l'chivara.
Why by a rope do you only say to make a handle
for a box, which is presumably larger than the strap for the
than the strap for the sieve? Rope you can also use to
make a strap for a sieve, so you should go by a
smaller amount. So the גמרא Gemara says no: כיון דחריק במנא. keivan
de-charik b'mana. No, since it since it like rubs up against the
vessel and it sort of is abrasive, לא עבדי אינשי. lo avdi
inshi. You don't make it for your sieve, which is apparently you
know a not cheap thing. A box you would make it for,
but you wouldn't make it for a sieve, you want something that's
going to be less abrasive to be the strap. תנו רבנן. Tano
rabanan. So our Rabbis taught: הוצין
כדי לעשות אזן לסל וכפיפה. hutzin k'dei laasot ozen l'sal ve-khfifa. So
הוצין, hutzin, which is like basically of like wicker, you know, is
is that what you call it? That stuff you make out of
like those
it's wicker, right? Okay, fine. Anyway, you know, wicker is in order
to in order to make a an ear like a handle for
a סל וכפיפה, sal ve-khfifa, which is basically a wicker basket. So
what you would use to to make a handle for a wicker
basket, wicker. So that amount in order to do that.
כפיפה מצרית. k'fifa mitzrit. סיב. siv. Now how about סיב? siv? סיב
siv is some type of a like hairy substance that grows presumably
between the bark and the trunk
of a of a what do you call it? Of a of
a palm tree. So what would you use that for? אחרים אומרים.
acherim omrim. Others say. It's interesting, nobody he's not arguing with anybody,
but here's his here's what he said about this: כדי ליתן על
פי מכבק קטן לסנן את היין k'dei litein al pi machbak katan
l'sanein et ha-yayin to put by the mouth of a small pitcher
in order to sieve out the—to use be a sieve for the
wine. So apparently they would put some type of a fibrous stringy
material by the mouth of a pitcher, you pour it through it,
and it serves as a filter for your wine. Okay, so that's
the amount to use for that type of a wine filter. It's
very interesting. I mean you get a real feel for like the
realia of their—I mean I you know it's hard to always fully
get what they're talking about, but you really are seeing about you
know the the reality of their of how they lived. רבב revav
כדי לסוך תחת אספגין קטנה. k'dei lasuch tachat aspagin ktana. So how
about if you have like a type of a schmaltz, you know
basically like you know meat fat or whatever, so to put underneath
a small wafer in the oven. You know, like spray Pam on
your on your you know put a little oil on so it
doesn't stick? So you put a little schmaltz underneath the wafer. וכמה
שיעורה? ve-kama shiura? What is its size? רש"י Rashi says that means
not the size of the of the schmaltz, but the size of
the wafer. What type of a how big of a wafer to
put this under?
כסלע. k'sela. The amount—the wafer's the size of a סלע, sela, a
Greek coin. והתניא כגרוגרת? ve-hatanya k'grogaret? Didn't we say like a גרוגרת,
grogaret, which is this pressed fig? That seems to be coming up
everywhere. אידי ואידי חד שיעורה הוא. Iddi v'iddi chad shi'ura hu. Yeah,
that's basically the same size. Okay, so now we know that the
size of a pressed fig, at least the sort of surface area,
not the volume, is the same as, you know, the width and,
you know, the sort of, you know, the two-dimensional size is the
same as a סלע. sela. Okay now תוספות Tosafot by the way
asks a question. He says, I don't understand it, how are you
putting שמאלץ schmalz under a wafer? You're not allowed to have פליישיק
fleishig bread. There's an איסור issur to have פליישיק fleishig or מילכיג
milchig bread because we're afraid you'll come to eat it, you know,
you eat bread with everything, and you'll come to eat it with
the other gender.
So תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, but if it's like a small thing
or it's a thing that has a סימן siman that it's obviously
not bread, it's obviously some type of a cookie or something else,
then this הלכה halacha doesn't apply. It only applied to something that
was bread and wasn't sort of obvious, you know, what type of
a thing. Something that's clear that's more obvious that it's different is
okay.
Yeah,
but he understands that רבבה revava doesn't mean oil. He understands רבבה
revava specifically means a type of like a פליישיק fleishig שמאלץ, schmalz,
you know, fat. So then he asks that question. Okay so
that's the interesting issue. Like Thomas' English muffins, you know, whatever, this
is a whole חולין Chullin discussion. But I, most people aren't aware,
I don't know are people here aware that Thomas' English muffins are
OUD? They're dairy. They're really dairy, not the fake OUD, the real
dairy. So there's a question of like, you know, is that allowed?
Can you have dairy bread? You know, so first of all, there's
some people say can you have maybe if you have the D
on the packaging, that's enough of a סימן? siman? Because they say
you're allowed to have dairy bread when there's a סימן. siman. But
others say no no, it has to be different about the thing
itself. So but Thomas' English muffins are different that they've got all
that nooks and crannies, it doesn't look like normal bread. So anyway
those are interesting discussions. It's just interesting that תוספות Tosafot raises it
here and he would say look this is something that clearly isn't
bread or it's obvious that it's different, it's not a problem. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
מוכין, Muchin, if you have like little like, you know, sort of
like pieces of cloth or whatever, כדי לעשות כדור קטנה, k'dei la'asot
kadur katana, to make out of it a small ball. וכמה שיעורה,
V'kama shi'ura, how big is that ball? כאגוז, K'egoz, like the size
of a nut. I don't know exactly what you do with the
ball, maybe you give it to an infant to play with or
something like that. Okay so now we're moving on, so we added
a couple things that weren't in the משנה. mishnah נייר
כדי לכתוב עליו קשר מוכסין, Niyar k'dei lichtov alav kesher mochin, paper
to write on it the thing for the tax collector, the receipt
for the tax collector.
וכמה קשר מוכסין? V'kama kesher mochin? שתי אותיות. Shtei otiyot. How big
would the thing have to be? Two letters. Now the גמרא Gemara
assumes, you know, from actually has this גירסא girsa of קשר מוכסין,
kesher mochin, but the גמרא Gemara assumes that this means specific like
letters or symbols that they would use which are bigger than the
smaller size of normal letters. That's just the assumption the גמרא gemara
has. Okay, some very particular type of special symbol. ורמינהו, Ur'mihu, I'll
ask you on this: המוציא נייר חלק אם יש בו כדי לכתוב
שתי אותיות חייב, Ha'motzi niyar chalak im yesh bo k'dei lichtov shtei
otiyot chayav, if you take out blank paper, if you have enough
to write two letters, you're חייב, chayav אם לא פטור, im lo
patur, if not, you're exempt. And that sounds like your standard two
letters, right? Your standard two letters, that's normally defined as writing, like
for example, ink goes by enough ink to write your standard two
letters. So why by the קשר מוכסין kesher mochin do we say
the two sort of, you know, symbols of the tax collector, which
presumably is a different size than these two letters? And רש״י Rashi
says presumably a larger size. Shouldn't it just be enough to write
two simple letters? אמר רב ששת: Amar Rav Sheshet: מאי שתי אותיות,
שתי אותיות שקשר מוכסין. Mai shtei otiyot, shtei otiyot she'kesher mochin. No,
we don't here mean two normal letters. We mean two symbols, the
double-letter symbol of these tax collectors. Okay so that actually is what
we are talking about here. Which raises a question, which is why
is it not enough to write two letters on it, right? Why
specifically do you go by the tax collector's use and you don't
go by, you know, a normal type of a use? So it's
actually is interesting. I remember once in a different lifetime, when I
was more than like I think it was 15 years ago, so
anyway when I was in some class at Columbia about, you know,
the classical world and Roman society and the whole question about, you
know, the use, tax collectors. I remember anyway somehow this משנה mishna
came up. Anyway,
and you know, the professor pointed out like even paper, not only
was cloth expensive, even paper was expensive. I'm surprised it was even
in common use at this.
Yeah exactly. So I mean it did exist, but it was pretty
uncommon. So you know, he says it's pretty amazing that they were
using it for receipts for tax collectors, you know, because it was
it was a pretty it was not so common, you know, and
it was pretty expensive. So it could be, you know, that again,
that if you're taking out cloth which was used for מזוזה, mezuzah,
we already know that that's a larger size because it was so
expensive, it's a larger size to be used
for the פרשה parsha of שמע. Shema. So maybe paper was primarily
really just used, it wasn't as expensive as cloth, but you needed
to hold on to your receipt for your tax collector, that's what
it was used for. Other type of writing maybe you did like
on wax tablets. So you know, that's those are interesting discussions. It's
just interesting that תוספות Tosafot raises it here and he would say
look this is something that clearly isn't bread or it's obvious that
it's different, it's not a problem. What I'm trying to figure out
is why aren't you חייב chayav on normal paper for two letters?
Right, you know, why does it have to be specifically the tax
collector's symbols? And you know, maybe these the paper was really primarily
used for this was its primary use and other type of writing,
either like you know ritual writing like ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah was
done on קלף klaf and other types of writing maybe like like
I said, I think wax tablets and they used those types of
things, you know, and also let's remember it was an oral culture.
So they didn't have as much stuff that was written that was
not like ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah. So anyway, so the גמרא gemara's
says actually if it's paper, not two normal letters, only the two
letters of the tax collector and that according to רש״י Rashi is
a bigger size. Yes.
Did they only use one side of the paper?
So by קלף klaf I know that they did. I mean that
actually we'll discuss that later, the way the קלף klaf was processed,
most of the time only one side was usable. Paper I really
don't know. So you're saying if presumably yes because you're saying why
erased paper is it a different size, why don't you just use
the other side of the paper?
That might be true, but then but you know maybe I mean
they might have had like a particular you know symbol that was
conventional that they did and so that's just happens to be how
it was used, right, you know. So so like if you said
you know a size of a receipt to show like a ticket
stub for the movies, you wouldn't say well why don't you just
put stuff on both sides. The way they use it is they
do it this way. Okay, so that for for paper we don't
go by normal writing, we go specifically by how it was used
by tax collectors. So it says like this,
that's what רב ששת Rav Sheshet says. רבא אמר Rava amar, שתי
אותיות דידן. Now we're talking about our two normal letters.
So why is that so that's smaller than the two symbols or
letters of the tax collector? So no, ובית אחיזה. uveis achiza. It
doesn't just mean two letters, it means two letters plus the part
of the of the paper you have to hold on to while
you're writing it. So that makes it דהיינו כקשר מוכסין. dehaynu keshar
mochsinn. So that's equivalent to the size of the two tax collector
letters. So תוספות Tosafot says so why don't you have to factor
that in for the tax collector? So he says maybe they had
a way of writing that didn't require holding down. Again, maybe it
was more like a stamp. Okay, so you know for if so
for the tax so you have one size, that size is big
enough either for a stamp of the tax collectors or if you're
actually going to write on it yourself and normal writing then it's
big enough to hold and to write two letters. So according to
this answer I just think that this is interesting, it seems like
it's a you know whatever it's a technical debate, but according to
this answer they they would use paper for normal writing. You understand
that's the difference. According to one answer the only thing we consider
the paper for is the tax collector purpose. If you just for
the normal writing use that's not a standard enough use to be
as significant. According to this no it is enough, but because that
use requires also holding the paper therefore it's a little bit bigger
and that's equivalent to the size that they would use for the
tax collector receipt. Okay so this approach actually acknowledges that it or
says it would be used for this normal type of writing as
well. So now yes.
Is it talking about the prohibition of writing or the amount of
paper?
No, neither. We're talking about the prohibition of carrying, but how big
of a piece to carry. When we say two letters you're what
do you when you're חייב chayav. talking about the paper, the paper,
the paper, right, okay. So okay, so so those are the two
approaches, whether it's all about tax collectors or it's both they're equivalent
but it's either for our writing or for for tax collectors. Okay,
so now the גמרא gemara says like
this, מיתיבי, meiteivei, I'll ask from this: המוציא נייר מחוק ושטרא פרוע,
hamotzi neyar machuk ushtar parua, if you take out erased paper or
a a you know document
of that that you know that signifies a debt. There's got to
be a word for that. It's not an IOU, I mean it's
a real שטר, shtar, it's a real like you know writ that
basically of it's of that a writ of debt. There's got to
be a word for that. What? A note? I guess, okay. Anyway,
a anyway anyway so that's what a שטר shtar is. A שטר
shtar is basically it's it's the record that somebody borrowed money from
me
and and you know it's my proof that it's going to allow
me to collect. And it's it's like a real you know I
don't know what do you do I mean what do you do
now if you lend somebody money, bank lends you money, I mean
what you know what do they have you sign? Is it a
contract that you sign? That's a lot of paper. It's a contract
I guess you know but this was the officially registered document that
was the proof of note.
Yeah. In that stack of paper
right there's the thing that right
there's a thing that is like the title of the car right
right right.
So basically it's some type of you know of a note of
debt. Okay so that's what a שטר shtar is. Major major גמרות
Gemoras about the שטר, shtar, about you know how you prove that
it you know what how you write it how you sign it
how you prove it. Anyway obviously if you're lending money שטרות shtarot
are very important. So you have either a erased paper or a
paid off שטר. shtar. So once it's paid off obviously you can't
use it to collect again. So what are you going to do
with it?
אם יש בלבנו שלו im yesh beloveno shelo כדי לכתוב שתי אותיות
kdei lichtov shtei otiyos או בכולו כדי לכרוך על פי צלוחית קטנה
o bechulo kdei lachroch al pi tzluchis ktana של פ shel p
חייב. chayav. So what you use erased paper for or a paid-up
שטר, shtar, you use it either as a type of piece, just
like a not to write on but just a piece of paper
like to wrap around the opening of a bottle, you know, so
that's a very small amount, you use it as a bottle wrapper,
or if you have enough white space on it that you can
fit you know get two letters into some of the white space.
So in theory you could tear it off and use a piece
of it for your normal writing of two letters and presumably that's
roughly the same size, or it would seem because and then just
picks the one that's smaller. Okay, I thought that you
didn't have to have a שטר shtar
that's so small you can't write two letters on it, and the
שטר shtar is big, isn't it?
No, it's no, it's paid off. So so the only thing left
to be done with it is to try to tear off some
of the white space and use some of the white space, some
of the edges.
Oh, parts of it that's paid like like a גט. get.
Right. If the שטר shtar has no good no good usable white
space, it's possible you could carry the whole שטר shtar and be
פטור. pattur. It's a big it's a big piece of paper, but
it's not
usable now, not exactly because
if you could wrap it around you could still use it as
just like a piece of like you know like wrapping paper if
you could use it to wrap around the opening of a bottle
and you have enough for that use then you're חייב. chayav. So
what the משנה says is but it's a very tiny שטר. shtar.
It's a yeah I mean it's hard to imagine a שטר shtar
that is would not be big enough you know to wrap around
a bottle but maybe it means it's a fragment of a שטר.
shtar. Okay, so what you're saying is like this is that for
a שטר, shtar, what's the size? Either if you have white space
that you can write two letters, then that's one size. Or if
you don't have that white space, then if you can use it
to wrap around a bottle, it would seem either of those are
very small amounts. But anyway, and it's funny, it would seem once
there's white space to write two letters, there's got to be it's
got to be bigger than the you would think than the amount
to wrap around wrap around the opening.
Right, the opening of the bottle. It's got to be very tiny.
Yeah, I don't really get it. I got to tell you because
the point is having white space is a special case. So the
normal case would be if it's big enough to wrap around the
bottle, but if it has white space then of the space for
two letters. But if a שטר shtar that has white space for
two letters is going to be bigger then presumably than the amount
you need to wrap around the opening of the bottle. So I
really am not getting it but anyway, let's let's see what the
גמרא gemara says. So ואידך פטור. v'idach pattur. So again presumably this
is so this speaks about two letters. So let's take a look
what the גמרא's gemara's problem issue with it is. בשלמא לרב ששת
דאמר מאי שתי אותיות שתי אותיות שבקשר מוכסין שפיר. Bishlama l'Rav Sheshes
d'amar mai shtei osiyos shtei osiyos shebekesher mochsin shapir. So so
if according to Rav Sheshes said it says two letters means two
letters of the tax collectors, fine, that's what it means here too,
two letters of the tax collectors, no problem. Okay, so same type
of a size. אלא לרבא דאמר שתי אותיות דידן ובית אחיזה דהיינו
קשר מוכסין. Ella l'Rava d'amar shtei osiyos didan uveit achiza dehaynu kesher
mochsin. So
but according to Rava that says two letters of ours means two
letters plus the amount of space that you need to hold onto
it and that is the same as the size of like the
you know the for that's used for the tax collectors. הכא בית
אחיזה לא צריך. Hacha beit achiza lo tzarich. Here you don't need
a thing to hold because you've got the whole rest of the
שטר shtar to hold onto and you don't need a and you
don't need the white space to include the amount to hold. It's
a seems like a very funny question, right? Rava normally says that
if this is your paper, right? Let's let's start with somebody have
a pen I'll write two letters? Anyway, okay, it doesn't matter. Anyway,
you normally would go by the middle spot would be the write
two letters but you have to hold it as you're writing it,
and when it says two letters it means two letters plus the
holding space. What does this say? This says if you've got a
whole
שטר shtar here, right, and some white space here of two letters,
then you're חייב. chayav So the גמרא Gemara says if two letters
means two letters plus the holding space, why do you need two
letters plus the holding space? You have the whole rest of the
שטר shtar to hold onto. Which is not the world's biggest question.
So in this context it means just the two letters. In a
context where you don't have the rest of the שטר shtar it
means two letters plus the holding space. Anyway, that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. Now we're going to get into more interesting discussions about
around the issue of the שטר, shtar, yes.
But with a cancelled one that's already been used, right? Yes. What
about one that hasn't?
That we're going to get into that. Well one that hasn't, clearly
you're חייב chayav. if it can be used, right? The only question
is before after it's been cancelled, what use does it have?
Okay so maybe because it's an object of use?
Yeah, an object of yeah.
Or maybe it all has to do with like use, in other
words a used document doesn't really have a use anymore. Right. But
the paper doesn't have use so they're talking about the usable space.
Right. But the usable space is two letters and the question was,
right, it's tiny, and that's fine, but but the גמרא's Gemara question
is if two the space for two letters means two letters. plus
the space to hold on, that doesn't have to be incorporated here
because you can hold on to the rest of the שטר shtar
as you're writing.
Oh, I see. Yes, that's it.
Yeah, but the point is, exactly. But the point is, okay, so
in this context it means just two letters. And when you don't
have a rest of a שטר, shtar, it means two letters plus
the thing you hold on. All right, let's keep on going. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Here
it's going to get קשיא. kasha. תנו רבנן. Tano rabanan. המוציא קשר
מוכס עד שלא הראהו למוכס חייב. Hamosi kesher mochas ad shelo herau
lemochas chayav.
So if you, so this is sort of like the paid-off שטר.
shtar. If you have the receipt, so before you showed it to
the מוכס, mochas, I think the best way to sort of think
about this in contemporary ways is, you know, your ticket stub, you
know, to the movie. So before you actually got into the movie,
before you actually showed it, then you're חייב. chayav. משהראהו למוכס, Misheherau
lemochas, once you showed it to the guy, פטור, patur, then it's
not usable, and presumably it has no other use, so you're exempt.
Again, why don't you say the use about putting it on your
bottle stopper? That's not clear. But without worrying about the bottle stopper,
it's that once it's been used, it has no further use and
you're פטור. patur. רבי יהודה אומר אף משהראהו למוכס חייב. Rabi Yehuda
omer af misheherau lemochas chayav. Even after you've shown it to the
tax collector, you're חייב. chayav What use is it? מפני שצריך לו,
Mitnei shetzorech lo, because you have a use for it. That wasn't
so helpful. What use for do you have after you've shown it?
So מאי בינייהו, mai binaihu, what's the difference? So אמר אביי, amar
Abaye, איכא בינייהו רהיטי דמוכסא. ika binaihu rahiti mochsa. The difference is
the people that run after, after you, the tax runners, which means,
or maybe a better example is like, you know, you get on
to the, you get on to the bus, right, and you show
your ticket, and then afterwards they might have somebody walking around to
make sure that nobody skipped the fare and is on the bus
without the ticket, and you still need to hold on to your
receipt. Okay, so this is very nice that you first you showed
it to the tax collector, but they might run after you again,
somebody else, and you'll have to prove it, you need to hold
on to your receipt. So what does the other one say? So
רש"י Rashi says the other one says if somebody else runs after
me, I'll go back to the guy I showed my ticket to
and he can vouch for me. Must mean you assume that that
guy has a very good memory. Okay, רבא Rava אמר, רבא Rava
says, מוכסא גדול ומוכסא קטון איכא בינייהו. mochsa gadol mochsa katon ika
binaihu.
If there's like a senior tax collector and a junior one. So
basically, you know, the senior tax collector might sort of have the
junior one fill in for him, and then the junior one doesn't
know that you've already paid because you didn't pay him, you paid
the senior one, and therefore you're going to have to show it
to him. So all this I assume the way רש"י Rashi reads
it, that the guy you actually paid it to, or actually the
guy you actually showed the receipt to will remember you. So the
question is if he'll remember you, then after you showed him the
receipt why do you need it? And the point is well there
might be other people involved. There's a guy who runs around double
checking, there's a junior guy that fills in. So even if that
guy remembers you, you'll still need a receipt, there'll be somebody else
who will be involved. Okay,
fine. So now it goes on, ומוכסא קטון איכא בינייהו. u’mochsa katon
ika binaihu. רש"י Rashi by the way just so you're aware says
we're not just talking about like paying your income tax or whatever,
we're talking about a specific, more like a fee to cross a
river, to cross a bridge, so that's how רש"י Rashi understands this
what this means by
מוכס. mochas. רב אשי אמר חד מוכס איכא בינייהו מפני שצריך להראותו
למוכס שני. Rav Ashi amar chad mochas ika binaihu, mipnei shetzorech lo
leharoso lemochas sheni. No, no, no, even if there's only one guy
who you have to show it you know who you have to
show it to and he's not going to run, nobody else is
going to run after you, there's not going to be any junior
person, you still want to hold on to your receipt. Why? Because
you want to show it in a different scenario to other tax
collectors. דאמר ליה חזי דגברא דמוכסא אנא De’amlei chazi de’gavre de’mochas ana
look I'm a trustworthy guy. Here's the evidence, I've always paid my
taxes, you know, it's like the guy, you know, you take out
your, you know, your tax returns, you know, you can look at
my tax returns, you can see I'm a tax-paying citizen, etc. So
even if you don't need it for this immediate purpose, you want
to hold on to it as just general evidence that you are
a law-abiding citizen. Okay, תנו רבנן. Now we get to the שטר
shtar and also this interesting discussion. You know, for me it's a
lot easier when it stops talking about the reality and just starts
talking about like legal concepts. So here we get to this issue
about a שטר shtar that's already been paid. Let's take a look.
המוציא שטר חוב, Hamosi shtar chov, you take out a, you know,
a writ, a document of debt. עד שלא פרעו חייב. Ad shelo
perau chayav. Until before the loaner has paid it, the debtor has
paid it, so you're חייב chayav. because it's a document of real
value, you're going to use it to collect. משהפרעו Misheperau once it's
been paid off, פטור, patur, then you're exempt because it has no
value. Why can't you use it as a bottle stopper? Not so
clear, we might see why in a minute. רבי יהודה אומר אף
משהפרעו חייב מפני שצריך לו. Rabi Yehuda omer af misheperau chayav mitnei
shetzorech lo. Same type of debate, even if it's been paid, you
still want to hold on to it, it has a use. So
מאי בינייהו, mai binaihu, what's their debate about? And now we get
into a much more interesting like legal discussion. אמר רב יוסף, amar
Rav Yosef, אסור לשהות שטר פרוע איכא בינייהו. assur lishos shtar parua
ika binaihu.
Whether there's a prohibition to hold on to a paid-up document. You
could understand why there's a prohibition because, you know, you can come
and try to collect twice, and maybe the guy has a receipt,
maybe he doesn't, maybe he won't remember, you know, and there's even
a prohibition maybe for to give the document to the, to the,
to the debtor because the debtor will hold on to it but
then he might lose it. And then somebody will return it to
the to the creditor, and then again, it'll be too dangerous. So
a paid-up שטר shtar is dangerous to have around, and therefore that's
the question. Okay, רבנן סברי Rabanan savri אסור להשהות שטר פרוע. assur
lehashot shtar parua. You can't use it for anything. It's dangerous to
have around. And therefore, it has absolutely no use. And by the
way, רש"י Rashi says this also explains why we don't mention the
bottle stopper use. Because you can't even use it as a bottle
stopper. We do not allow anybody to hold onto a paid-up שטר.
shtar. It's just too dangerous to have around. Okay, so therefore fine,
it has no use. I'm פטור. patur. ורבי יהודה סבר Ve'Rabbi Yehuda
savar מותר להשהות שטר פרוע. mutar lehashot shtar parua. You are allowed
to have it hang around.
Maybe the the debtor will have a receipt, and or maybe the
the debtor is the one that's using it. You gave the שטר
shtar back to the debtor and he's allowed to have it around.
He has to be responsible. So therefore, if you can have it
around, it has a use. Now how big of a size? So
רש"י says fine. So now for bottle stopper, you know, that's the
size now. It's not usable as a שטר, shtar, but since you
as long as you're allowed to keep on holding it, you can
use it as a bottle stopper and therefore you'll be חייב. Okay,
that's one way of framing this debate. Okay, אביי אמר Abaye amar
דכולי עלמא אסור להשהות שטר פרוע. d'chulei alma assur lehashot shtar parua.
Everybody says you cannot hold onto a document that has been paid
up, even the creditor, even the debtor cannot hold onto it. והכא
במודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו קמיפלגי. Vehacha bemodeh beshtar sheketavo tzarich lekayemo
kamiflagi. Very famous debate in other גמרות, Gemarot, which is if you
admit that a שטר shtar has been written, does it still need
to to have קיום? kiyuum? קיום kiyuum means that the signatures have
been verified. Okay, so basically here's what happens. I take out this
writ that says that you know that רבקה Rivka owes me a
hundred dollars, borrowed a hundred dollars. It has two witnesses on it.
Now רבקה Rivka can say, 'I think you forged that. I never
borrowed a hundred dollars from you.' Okay, so what would I have
to do? I'd have to go get people that recognize those signatures
and say, 'Yeah, that is ראובן's Reuven signature. That is שמעון's signature.'
Once I've proven that I didn't forge the signatures, that the guy
who signed his name, it is his genuine signature, right? Right now
you know it's like you go to a notary as you're signing
something, right, as evidence you are the person who signed it. So
basically, so I would get it notarized and then I would be
able to collect from רבקה. Rivka. Now let's say I go ahead
and I take this שטר shtar and I say to רבקה, Rivka,
'Here, you owe me a hundred dollars.' And רבקה Rivka says, 'I
paid it. Yeah, you're right. That was a שטר, shtar, but I
paid it up and I forgot to get the שטר shtar back.
You said wait till I go get it, whatever. But I paid
it up.' Now do we believe her? She says she paid it,
but she can always say she paid it. I have the document.
The only thing is that the document does not have the signatures
notarized. So the normal assumption would be fine. I'll go, I'll notarize
the signatures. Now I have a you know, a real solid שטר,
shtar, and she can't she can't say she paid it. She doesn't
have any evidence. I win. Okay, but there's an opinion in the
גמרא Gemara that what is she doing when she says she's paid
she paid it? She's already implicitly admitting that what? That she borrowed
and that this is a legitimate שטר. shtar. So she's מודה בשטר
שכתבו. modeh beshtar sheketavo. She admitted that the שטר shtar was written.
So אין צריך לקיימו. ein tzarich lekayemo. I no longer have to
notarize it. Thank you very much. You've admitted it's a good שטר
shtar and now I have the evidence and you're not believed. Now
the other person says what the same way she's believed to say
it was a good שטר, shtar, she's believed to say that she
had paid it up. Okay, so that's the question when she says
she paid it, do I still need to notarize it or not?
Isn't the same thing like a גט, get, like they do in
the גט? get? Yeah. The גט get is given, it's cut. They
cut it and that's a sign that it's been given. Wouldn't they
do the same thing with that?
Yeah, it doesn't sound like it. It sounds like from the גמרא
that either what they would do is they would return it to
the לוה loveh or they would write a receipt.
I'm saying they would leave it...
I mean
that's definitely done with a גט. get. Right, right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. I'm just saying right, right, right, right.
You know, you know, I'll check, but that's not the assumption that
this גמרא's working with. Okay, so let's take a look. והכא במודה
בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו קמיפלגי. Vehacha bemodeh beshtar sheketavo tzarich lekayemo kamiflagi.
תנא קמא סבר, Tana Kama savar, the תנא קמא Tana Kama holds
מודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו. modeh beshtar sheketavo tzarich lekayemo. That even
when you admit it, I still have to get it notarized. By
the way, the other thing you have to be aware of is
that a lot of this was private exchanges. Did not happen in
front of a בית דין, Beit Din, right? I can a normal
exchange would be I came to you with the שטר, shtar, you
gave me the money, you asked for the שטר shtar back or
whatever. So you might be right, the cutting it, like the question
is was it a convention, not like was it a חיוב chiyuv
to cut, but like was it... so anyway, that's not the assumption
here. Let's take a look. והכא במודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו קמיפלגי.
Vehacha bemodeh beshtar sheketavo tzarich lekayemo kamiflagi. תנא קמא סבר מודה בשטר
שכתבו צריך לקיימו. Tana Kama savar modeh beshtar sheketavo tzarich lekayemo. That
even when you admit it, I still have to get it notarized.
ורבי יהודה סבר מודה בשטר שכתבו אין צריך לקיימו. Ve'Rabbi Yehuda savar
modeh beshtar sheketavo ein tzarich lekayemo. I don't have to get it
notarized. Okay, so how does that play
play in? ומה עד שלא פרעו ומשפרעו? Umai ad shelo parao umisheparao?
What does it mean that before and after it's been paid? It
doesn't literally mean before and after it's been paid. Here's what it
means. Top of ע"ט עמוד א'. Ayin-Tet Amud Aleph. עד שיאמר לא
פרעתי ולא פרעתי, Ad sheyomar lo parati velo parati, whether the guy
has said he's paid or not. So here... So here's the way
it reads: If the guy has not said he's paid, then obviously
the שטר shtar is of value. I'm going to use it to
collect my debt. But if the guy has said that he's paid,
so if I can still notarize it and collect my debt, then
it's still of value to me. But if I can't notarize it,
so even though he said he's paid, right? But if I can't
notarize it, then, then, I'm sorry, I just, so, okay, so,
so he's said he's paid. So the question is: will, okay, will
I ever be able to collect a שטר shtar that this guy
says he's paid? So if I have the ability to notarize it,
then of course I'll be able to collect, I'll get it notarized.
So רש"י and תוספות or תוספות more explicitly says that we have
to assume that I do not have the ability to notarize it,
okay? So I've got a שטר shtar which nobody recognizes these guys'
signatures, I don't have the ability to notarize it, that's the scenario.
Is it of value? So if you haven't yet said that you've
paid or not paid, and so it's a value, I'm going to
use it to collect. But once you've said you've paid and I
can't notarize it, is it of any value to me? What am
I going to use it for? You said you paid, I can't
notarize it. So the גמרא says, so if I say, so here's
the difference: if I have to notarize it, then it's of no
value to me. But if once you said you paid, that's implicitly
like you've notarized it for me because you said you paid, then
it is of value. Is that clear? Or have I lost people?
It sounds like I think I've lost people. Okay, we're going to,
you know what? We will continue with this. It's too interesting to
rush through, so we're going to, we'll pick up on the top
of עין ט' Ayin Tes tomorrow, okay? We'll end here for now.
All right.
Yeah.
That's that case where it's implicitly notarized because you admit that you
borrowed money, so now it's of that value. Exactly.
Anyway, I just, I just want to give us a little bit
more time.